Alright, so we'll start again from the beginning of the משנה Mishna
*Mishnah* here. So let's do it. אמר הממונה *Amar hamemuneh*, so the
ממונה Memuneh *memuneh* said, beginning here in the third פרק perek *perek*,
the ממונה Memuneh *memuneh* said, באו והפיסו *Bo'u vehifisu*, come and take
part in the lottery. מי השוחט *Mi hashohet*, who is the one
which will get to do the שחיטה shechitah, *shechita* of the תמיד
tamid. *Tamid*? מי הזורק *Mi hazorek*, who will do the זריקה zrikah,
*zrika* of the blood, throwing the blood? It doesn't mention קבלת הדם
*kabalat hadam* and הולכת הדם *holachat hadam*, that was all the same
person.
So it was interesting, it was the מקבל *mekabel* and the person
who caught the blood also brought it to the מזבח mizbeach, *mizbeach*
and also did the זריקת הדם *zrikat hadam*. Okay, all those are
the same person. Okay. מי מדשן מזבח הפנימי mizbe'ach hapenimi *Mi medashen
mizbeach hapnimi*, who is going to remove the ashes from the inner
מזבח mizbei'ach *mizbeach*? מי מדשן את המנורה *Mi medashen et hamenorah*, who
is going to remove the ashes from the מנורה menorah *menorah*? Okay,
it's interesting like sometimes verbs are used to mean remove as opposed
to to do, right? Like להשריש *lehashrish* means to
in Hebrew to mean to strike roots and it can mean to
uproot, right? Or like if you ever have some type of peanuts,
they could be shelled and salted, right? Which means the shells are
removed and the salt is put on. So anyway, מדשן *medashen* here
means to remove the ashes, yes.
שחיטה shechitah *Shechitah* could be done by a non-כהן kohein. *non-Kohen*. I
was going to ask.
It could be, but it wasn't. Okay. Certainly not for the תמיד
tamid. *Tamid*. I don't know if you brought your own קרבן korban.
*korban* and you said I want to choose to do the שחיטה
shechitah *shechita* of my own קרבן korban *korban* if they would let
you do it or not. You certainly, I mean in principle could,
but for the תמיד tamid *Tamid*, no, they would do the תמיד
tamid? *Tamid*. Yeah, no, that's the other question.
For instance,
let's say I bring my קרבן Korban, *korban* and I don't feel
like doing the שחיטה shechitah. *shechita*. They're not going to do a
lottery every time someone comes with a שחיטה shechitah
*shechita* and a זריקה zerika, *zrika*. No, no, no. So that's a
good point. The lottery was only done for the early עבודות *avodot*
of the day. It was done for also these types of things
which are the communal קרבנות korbanot, *korbanot*. Although it's true there are
other communal aspects like when there's a מוסף *Musaf*, right?
Now I have to remember because it is true for example that
the משנה mishna *Mishnah* in סוכה *Sukkah* says that by the מוסף
*Musaf* of קרבן korban, *korban* of סוכה *Sukkah* that there was a
lottery and they did make sure because there were seventy פרי החג
*pareih hachag* and there were and there were twenty-four משמרות *mishmarot*. And
it says that each משמר *mishmar* got to do
three
of the פרי החג *pareih hachag* minus two, meaning 3 x 24
is 72, so all except two got to do three. And it
does say, and those two, and it does say that those were,
right, I mean one of the things of פזר קשב *Pezar keshev*,
the way שמיני עצרת *Shemini Atzeret* is רגל בפני עצמו *regel bifnei
atzmo*, is פיס בפני עצמו *payis bifnei atzmo*, you start a new
lottery for its
for the מוספים *musafim*. So there would be a פיס *payis* for
the מוספים *musafim*. There'll be a פיס *payis* for this. The communal
stuff, again, whether it's all, everything that was communal I'd have to
check, but basically the communal aspects were done with a פיס *payis*.
And then when individuals brought, that was,
you know what was just like I saw first?
Yeah, there must have been a floor manager. Okay, I'm serious, to
keep things moving, assigned jobs. But it's a very good point. The
פיסות *payisot* were done here in the morning and they were done
primarily for like the communal aspects. They were not done for everything
that was done.
Okay. So, back to beginning here third פרק perek. דף ל' *perek
Daf Lamed*, we pick, we return. So it says, oh and I
by the way the משנה *Mishnah* in שקלים *Shekalim* that says הממונה
על הפיסות *hamemuneh al hapaysot* was like a, it names the person,
it's so-and-so was the הממונה על הפיסות *hamemuneh al hapaysot*. So it
sounds like it was like a year-long regular position. Alright, not permanently,
well at least for a while.
I mean if it's naming a person, it didn't mean just for
one year.
Right, right, right. So it sounds like it was pretty permanent. Okay.
So מי השוחט *Mi hashohet*, who's going to do the שחיטה shechitah.
*shechita*? מי הזורק *Mi hazorek*, who זריקת הדם *zrikat hadam*? מי מדשן
מזבח הפנימי Mizbe'ach Hapnami *Mi medashen mizbeach hapnimi*, who removes the ashes
from the inner מזבח mizbei'ach *mizbeach*? That's three. מי מדשן המנורה *Mi
medashen hamenorah*, who removes the ashes from the מנורה menorah, *menorah*? Four.
מי מעלה אברים לכבש *Mi ma'aleh evarim lakevesh*, who is going to
bring the limbs of the עולה olah. *olah*, the עולת תמיד olat
tamid, *olat tamid*, which is what this מסכת *masechet* is about, to
the ramp? So first a group of כהנים kohanim *kohanim* bring it
from the floor to the ramp and midpoint in the ramp, and
then another group bring it from the midpoint on the ramp to
the top of the מזבח mizbei'ach, *mizbeach*. Now that is, that is
going to be a lot of כהנים kohanim *kohanim* are going to
be involved. So far we have four prior to the bringing of
the limbs. Now let's count the bringing of the limbs. הראש והרגל
harosh veharegel *Harosh veharegel*, the head and
the foreleg.
This is a subset of the מעלה אברים *ma'aleh evarim*. Yeah, this
right, this is a list of all the כהנים Kohanim: *kohanim* of
all the people that were מעלה אברים *ma'aleh evarim*. So number one,
somebody who brings the הראש והרגל *harosh veharegel*, the head and the
foreleg, של ימין *shel yamin*, the right foreleg. That's one person.
Okay, ושתי הידיים *vushtei hayadayim*.
I know,
one person does the whole thing. It's definitely, yeah.
But he goes back and forth.
I know, the weight distribution here does not seem to be equal.
They wouldn't bring it at the same time, we would all do
the הראש *harosh* and go back?
I don't think so, the sense you get is that it's at
the same time, it's at the same time. Okay, ושתי הידיים *vushtei
hayadayim*, now the two hands, excuse me, I said the foreleg but
I did not mean the, well, they call hands the two that
are on the front and legs the two. that are on the
back. Okay, so the head and the rear leg, the right rear
leg, בשתי הידיים, bishtei hayadayim, that's one portion. בשתי הידיים, bishtei hayadayim
the two forelegs, for arms, whatever, is the next
כהן. Kohen. העוקץ והרגל של שמאל, ha'uketz veharegel shel smol, the tail
and the left leg, the left rear leg, that's three people.
החזה והגירה, hachazeh vehageirah, the chest and the, like this is like
the throat,
the, the, the trachea, I don't know if the trachea, the esophagus,
the stuff that goes down into the throat. It comes together with—hold
on, let me just check the מפרש mefaresh here. He says which
inner organs it comes with.
Hold on. Let me see חזה chazeh
here. The
fat of the chest
and the עוקץ uketz of the chest.
That is not what it sounds like.
One minute. Okay.
Yeah, so this says that it comes also together with the heart,
which is interesting, because the heart is not directly attached to the
trachea and the esophagus, and
the liver and the heart. Anyway, okay, with some of—yeah, you would
think as the lungs. Okay, so anyway, so the chest and some
and the throat and some of the organs in the thoracic—is that
right? Thoracic? Did I get that right? Thoracic cavity. There's my high
school biology. Okay. So that's number three.
ושתי דפנות, ushtei defanot, the two flanks, you know, from the upper,
from the upper
body. That's four. הקרביים, hakirvayim, the inner organs is five. And including
the heart and
the lungs and the liver?
Yeah, what,
what was left?
Like the intestines or something? Yeah. Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, like the,
yeah, the stomach and all those intestines. Right. So that's five.
Am I off here?
You're off by one. You're off by one.
Number six. That's six. What did I miss?
Let's see the—did I miscount?
Yeah. Okay, fine. Let's do it. הראש והרגל is one. בשתי הידיים
is two. עוקץ והרגל של שמאל uketz veharegel shel smol is three.
חזה וגרה chazeh vegeirah is four. שתי דפנות shtei defanot is five.
Got it. Okay, two flanks is five. קרביים, kirvayim, inner organs are
six. So that's six. Good. So we had four before this, plus
this six, so we're up to ten. והסולת, vehasolet, the person who
brings the flour that comes with the, you know, מנחה mincha that
comes with the קרבן. Korban והחביתין, veha-chavitin, which is the מנחה mincha
of the כהן גדול, kohein gadol, which is brought, you know, right
at the same time or roughly at the same time of the
תמיד. tamid
והיין, vehayayin, the wine which comes with as part of the מנחת
נסכים minchat nesachim that comes with the עולת תמיד, tamid comes with
every עולה. Okay, that is three more. Three more. So now we're
up to thirteen. There you go. Just like I told you. Okay.
חביתין, chavitin, yeah, so those are the ones that are distributed. Now,
one second. You think that this is also the order in which
it's done. But as we're going to see, it's not exactly the
order. It mentions שוחט shochet and זורק zoreik first, and those were
the first ones that were awarded the, you know, first right as
it—you know, they were the ones that the first guy in the
lottery got שחיטה, shechting the next guy got זריקה, but as we
will see, they actually did the דישון מזבח הפנימי dishun mizbeach hapnimi
and the דישון המנורה dishun hamenorah before they actually got around to
doing the שחיטה shechita of the תמיד. tamid So we start with
awarding the תמיד tamid first because that's the focus, but the order
actually is a little out of order of the way it was
done. The דישון dishun starts first, and we will see that in
a minute. Yes.
So one that's missing is the person who actually cuts up the
animal into pieces.
Yeah, that is a very good point.
Maybe there's actually a person who's assigned to do that, because that's
a skill.
Yeah, that is a real skilled labor. Yeah, yes.
שחיטה shechting isn't?
Yeah, it's a good point. It's a good point. But maybe I
think all the כהנים kohanim, knew how to do שחיטה. shechita But
you're right. I mean, maybe all the כהנים should have known how
to cut things up because it would often, because every קרבן Korban
would get cut up. Not everyone would get—only all the עולות olot
would get cut up, you know, like this. And certainly everyone would
get cut up to remove the inner, the inner st... it's a
good point, you know. Clearly not everything was, either because of what
Michael says, either because some stuff required specialized skill or or because
some stuff was maybe not seen as as coveted as the others.
I don't know. It's an interesting question. But it's a very good
point.
But my understanding is these חביתין chavitin are חביתי כהן גדול? chaviti
kohein gadol? Yes. So with the תמיד? tamid. Yeah. He wouldn't bring
his own?
I mean, like, I kind of got... He was not always present.
They'd be brought for him. He did not, he was...
So he, so he doesn't want to do it on his own.
He could do it on his own.
Yeah, but it sounds like they would have it taken care of
on a regular basis. I mean, if he actually wanted to take
it and bring it up on the מזבח, mizbei'ach maybe he could.
He could do anything. Yeah, כהן גדול, kohein gadol, whatever he wants
to do, he gets to do. Okay. So if you remember, we
learned in the last פרק that they got started cooking the water
and getting ready for the חביתין chavitin even as they were doing
the תרומת הדשן. terumat hadeshen. Right. So all that was taking place
for him.
I
kind of
think that if it's his חביתין, chavitin, he should, like, you know,
be doing this on his own. He should be in there every
day. You would think. You would think. Okay. You know, it's some
of the—it's good to be the כהן גדול. kohein gadol. Okay. he
slightly misquotes Mel Brooks. We go down. Okay. הפיסו, Hefisu, so they
did the lottery. זכה מי שזכה, Zacha mi she-zacha, so whoever got
it got it, whoever won the lottery won it. אמר להם Amar
lahem and all the rest and all the rest followed. אמר להם.
Amar lahem. So now the ממונה Memuneh says to them: צאו וראו
אם הגיע זמן שחיטה, Tze'u u-re'u im higia zeman shechitah, go out,
now because they're in this room, right? They're so they're inside of
a room. Go out and see if the time of שחיטה shechita,
has come because it has to be, and not sunrise,
but at least it has to be light. It has to be
the morning star, עלות השחר alot hashachar to do שחיטה. shechita אם
הגיע צאו
וראו אם הגיע, if it was the time. הרואה אומר, Haro'eh omer,
the person on watch, which is interesting, we don't exactly know who
was that person. Like we talked about all the שומרים, shomrim, was
this one of the שומרים shomrim that was left on top of
the roofs? Because they would שומר shomer on the roofs. Maybe one
of them was left there to keep a lookout for the morning,
for the first rays of light. So הרואה אומר, Haro'eh omer, he
said ברקאי, barkai, which meant, it's
like בוקר, boker, some type of an exclamation which meant, like, it's
shown forth. מתיא בן שמואל אומר, Matya ben Shmuel omer, now מתיא
בן שמואל Matya ben Shmuel says: האיר פני כל המזרח, He'ir p'nei
kol hamizrach, has the entire eastern sky lit up? עד שבחברון Ad
she-be-Chevron to reach חברון? Chevron? הוא אומר הין. Hu omer hen. Yes.
Now there's an interesting question, who's saying what? Meaning מתיא בן שמואל
Matya ben Shmuel according to one משנה was the ממונה על הפייסות.
Memuneh al ha-payasot. So some say that this is not quoting him
as a תנא, Tanna, it's quoting him as a כהן. And it's
actually saying that he used to say this thing, meaning maybe the
others, after when he was no longer doing it, before him and
after him, they just said ברקאי. barkai. They asked did it light
up and the guy said ברקאי. barkai. But when he was on
the job, he said to the watch person, has the entire eastern
sky lit up? And then it sounds like he said עד שבחברון,
ad she-be-Chevron, that that's part of his question. But again according to
another
version, that there was actually a back and forth like this, that
he said, hold on let me actually double check this, for
a minute.
Yeah, hold on.
Yeah, it says the other way, that the person on the roof
said the entire east has lit up, according to the way it
is in יומא, Yoma, the one on the roof said the entire
east has lit up and מתיא בן שמואל Matya ben Shmuel or
whoever the ממונה Memuneh was said, "All the way to חברון?" Chevron?
and then he said yes. So there was more like of a
back and forth asking if all the way to חברון. Chevron. And
it actually says that the reason that they asked, "Can you see
all the way to חברון?" Chevron? was to remember the זכות אבות
zechut avot in the context of the קרבנות, korbanot, which raises a
whole interesting theme because our whole question is תפילה כנגד אבות, tefillah
keneged avot, כנגד קרבנות. keneged korbanot. So I think there's an interesting
thing beyond the זכות אבות zechut avot of bringing in the whole
context of the אבות, avot, which it wasn't by the אבות avot
it really wasn't about קרבנות, korbanot. it was about תפילה, tefillah, so
there's also, brings that theme in. Anyway, interesting. So the person on
the roof, meaning you've got the ממונה Memuneh saying, "Go check if
it's lit up," and the guy on the roof says, "Yeah, ברקאי."
barkai. Or according to another version the guy on the roof says,
"Oh, the whole east is lit up," and the ממונה says, "Really,
all the way to חברון?" Chevron? and he says yes. And the
reason according to another
discussion, the reason why he did this was that once they thought
it was the morning star and it wasn't, and they slaughtered the
תמיד tamid, and the whole thing was פסול pasul because they slaughtered
it before it was actually light. Okay. So that's, they make sure
it's light. אמר להם, Omer lahem, so then he says,
the ממונה says to the כהנים: צאו והביאו טלה מלשכת הטלאים, Tze'u
ve-havi'u taleh me-lishkat hatla'im, go get a sheep from the chamber of
sheep, which is where the sheep were kept four days prior to
check to make sure they were without blemishes. והרי לשכת הטלאים נתונה
במקצוע צפונית מערבית. Ve-harei lishkat hatla'im netunah be-mikto'a tzafonit maaravit.
Now
the chamber of sheep was in the northwest. Now this would sound
like it was an independent chamber, but from other sources it's clear
that it was a chamber in the בית המוקד. Beit Hamoked. If
you take a look here the בית המוקד, Beit Hamoked, right? One
of them says in this picture טלאים, t'la'im, sheep. Okay. Now by
the way when it says it was in the northwest, it's because
the entire בית המוקד Beit Hamoked was in the northwest. The actual
chamber of sheep was in the relative to the בית המוקד Beit
Hamoked here was actually in the southwest. Okay, but the בית המוקד
Beit Hamoked was in the northwest. Okay. So he's, so this, go
bring a sheep
from, they keep live animals
there making they're defecating, they're defecating.
It's an interesting question. I don't know, maybe they grazed them during
the day and at night they penned them up there. It's a
good question. I don't know. And how many? Well I
think only four, because they would keep, they'd check them for four
days. So you would remove one, you'd put another one in and
you'd start checking it. So each day you check them all each
day. Where'd they go to the rest room? Maybe they were only
purchased from the shepherds on, I don't know, do they keep the
whole flock? Maybe they had a flock and they kept them in
a
pen...
That's a good question.
Oh, you ask such good
questions.
All right, בברייתא B'varaita לשכת הטלאים Lishkat Hatlaim so it was
in the northwest, at least that's where the whole בית המוקד Beit
Hamoked was. ארבע לשכות היו שם. Arba lishchot hayu sham. Now there
were four chambers. Again, the
שם sham is
not clear, the reference, but the context is four chambers in the
בית המוקד. Beit Hamoked. So there was a huge, you know, room,
house, like a בית המוקד Beit Hamoked and had these four chambers
within it. אחת לשכת הטלאים, Achat Lishkat Hatlaim, one for the sheep.
ואחת לשכת החותמות Ve'achat Lishkat Hachotamot for the seals. What was the
story about the seals? The story was חותמות Chotamot no, the story
made well what? That they buried the חותמו
של Chotamo shel no.
The story of the
seals was was that if you wanted to get your no no,
your מנחות Menachot your
נסכים Nesachim for the for your קרבן, you would go to this
chamber. Now again, it's not exactly clear to me because normally ישראל
Yisrael would not be allowed past the עזרת ישראל. Ezrat Yisrael. This
is well into the עזרת כהנים. Ezrat Kohanim. So I don't know
if you sent somebody or they actually let you go to that
chamber. I guess no I guess, oh, you can come from the
outside! Ah, ah, you're right! Okay. So very good, right, right, that's
the explanation. If you look at it, yes, you can access the
chamber of חותמות Chotamot from the outside. And actually the gate there
was called שער הקרבן Sha'ar Hakorban and and maybe for this reason,
maybe for the sheep, but maybe because what you would do is
you'd go into that chamber yeah, that's the explanation. You'd go from
the outside and you'd stay on the part that wasn't the half
that was not בקדושת עזרה. bikdushat azara. So you'd go, you'd pay
your money, they'd give you a פתק, petek, they'd give you a
חותם, chotam, like a receipt. And then you would use this receipt
when you went to to bring your קרבן, you'd give them the
receipt and then they would provide the oil and the flour and
the wine for the מנחת נסכים. minchat nesachim.
Because you can't
you could have brought it yourself, but this was just an efficient
way of doing that. So that's a very good point. Maybe there
actually was even this was the way you went, you know, you
went to the front to the front. Maybe you first passed by
here, you know, you got your פתק petek and then you continued
on to the front. So that was the that was the room
that was the chamber of the seals. ואחת לשכת בית המוקד. Ve'achat
Lishkat Beit Hamoked.
That's the פתק? petek? The seal is a
פתק?
petek? Yeah, yeah, חותם, chotam, right, like a receipt. And then the
chamber of the בית המוקד, Beit Hamoked, which is where they would
have a fire. Of course, they presumably they also have a main
fire in the middle, so it's not exactly clear why a separate
chamber is called that. ואחת לשכה שעושים בה לחם הפנים, Ve'achat lishka
she'osim bah lechem hapanim, and the other, which is in the קודש,
kodesh, is where they actually would bake the לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim.
Okay? There's a lot of fires going on here, a lot of
nice warmth and heat, so they would bake the לחם הפנים lechem
hapanim in that. So, if you take a look at the picture,
you'll see that the one that is not name- mentioned- called בית
המוקד Beit Hamoked is ירידה לבית הטבילה. yerida l'veit hatvila. That was
also a chamber that had the underground passageway to get to the
to get to, you know, to get to the מקוה, mikvah, which
we talked about in the first פרק. Okay. So go get a
sheep from that chamber. נכנסו לשכת הטלאים. Nichnasu Lishkat Hatlaim. Now they
went to the so fine, presumably they're going to go to that
to get the sheep, but now they also went to a different
chamber and it doesn't tell us where that is, which is where
they stored all the כלי שרת. Klei Shareit. It's basically a storage
room, right, where you're going to keep all the כלי שרת. Klei
Shareit. הוציאו משם תשעים ושלושה כלי כסף וכלי זהב. Hotziu misham tishim
ushlosha klei kesef vechlei zahav.
They took out ninety-three different gold and silver
vessels. According to the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, it's ninety-three because in the נבואה
nevuah of חגי זכריה ומלאכי, Chaggai Zechariah u'Malachi, although according to some
it's only חגי ומלאכי, Chaggai u'Malachi, you can do the counting, it
says God's name ninety-three times. Okay? So I don't So anyway, ninety-
I don't know why that's relevant. Well, those were the נביאים nevi'im
that were around when they returned and built the second בית המקדש.
Beit Hamikdash. Anyway, they took out ninety-three gold and silver vessels. השקו
את התמיד בכוס של זהב. Hishku et hatamid bechos shel zahav. They
had it drink water from a gold goblet. We talked about this
yesterday. According to some that was an exaggeration. The reason they had
it drink water before they שחט-ed shacht it was apparently that would
make it easier to flay. אף על פי שהוא מבוקר מאמש, Af
al pi shehu mevukar me'emesh, although they checked it from blemishes from
the night before, because you would check these things actually for four
days, מבקרים אותו לאור אבוקות, mevakrim oto l'or avukot, they would check
it again now by the light of the torches. They would once
again do one final check. Now the fact that it says light
of the torches, according to at least the מפרש mefaresh here, the,
you know, he says that this checking and when he said go
get a sheep, this was actually before Or because they would check
these things actually for four days, מבקרין אותו לאור אבוקות, mevakrin oso
lo'ohr avukos, they would check it again now by the light of
the torches, they would once again do one final check. Now, the
fact that it says light of the torches, according to at least
a מפרש mefaresh here, the, you know, he says that this checking,
and when he said go get a sheet, this was actually before
the east lit up because as you see it's still dark, so
they're using torches. Of course, just because it's a little bit light
by the guy that's on the top of the roof can see
a little light, doesn't mean you don't still need some torchlight and
certainly the משנה makes it sound like no no no this was
already light and they were in the process of שחיטה so although
really only the שחיטה must be done once it's light, they only
it sounds like they only really got into in the process of
the תמיד tamid, when the when it was already light. Yes.
Also that they did it indoors with still in the chamber which
still might have been a dark room.
Oh, the checking. Oh that's interesting. That could be too. That could
be too.
Because they wouldn't want to take an animal out into the עזרה
azara and have to send it back.
That's a good point.
That's a good point. Okay. Incidentally, it says about this לשכת החותמות
lishkas hachosamos that that's where the חשמונאים chashmonaim sort of buried the
אבני מזבח.
avnei mizbei'ach. Right. So according to the גמרא gemara right that they
that when the מזבח mizbei'ach was defiled in the time of the
of you're right of the יוונים, yevanim, right that they they buried
some of the stones in that לשכה, lishka, that's correct, underneath the
floor.
Although here it doesn't look too buried, I mean although according to
that.
Okay. Now, מי שזכה בדישון מזבח הפנימי ובדישון המנורה. mi shezachah bedishun
mizbei'ach hapnimi uvdishun hamenorah. Now, ah,
so, okay, so we got the process of the תמיד tamid. started,
but and remember the first person that was awarded, by the way,
it doesn't say who is doing this process of going to sort
of Michael says in some of the things weren't in a in
a lot in a lottery, but it sounds like later that everybody
who has a part of שחיטה or bringing the תמיד tamid was
involved in all these processes around the תמיד. tamid Again I don't
know about the actual flaying and dismembering but certainly this process about
getting the sheep and checking him. Okay, but the first thing that
was handed out was the was the שחיטה and the זריקה, that's
going to not taken place yet. The next thing after that was
the cleaning of the ashes from the inner מזבח mizbeiach, and from
the מנורה menorah, and that's the first actual עבודה avodah that takes
place. So let's take a look. מי שזכה בדישון מזבח הפנימי ובדישון
המנורה, mi shezachah bedishun mizbei'ach hapnimi uvdishun hamenorah, the one that merited
the ones that merited the cleaning of the ashes of the inner
מזבח, Mizbe'ach, the golden מזבח Mizbe'ach. and the מנורה, menorah, היו מקדימים,
hayu makdimim, they would go forth first, they would, you know, do
their thing before everybody else. וארבעה כלים בידם, ve'arba'ah keilim beyadam, they
would have four vessels. הטני hateni which is a basket, הכוז hakuz
which is a type of like a
a pitcher, ושתי מפתחות ushtei maftichos and two and two keys. It's
interesting that it's called a כלי, kli, כלי kli you think is,
you know, not what you use to open the door, but okay,
what you use to do the עבודה. avodah. But anyway these were
the four things they would carry. הטני, hateni, the basket, דומה לתרקב
domeh letarkav was like a container of a תרקב tarkav which is
שלושה קבים, shlosha kabim, a שלושה קבים shlosha kabim container was a
standard size container. Actually they say תרקב תרי וקב, tarkav trei vekav,
תרי וקב trei vekav so it was שלושה קבים. shlosha kabim. של
זהב, shel zahav, it was gold. מחזיק קביים וחצי, machzik kabayim vachetzi,
it wasn't exactly שלושה קבים shlosha kabim which was the standard size
container, it was two and a half קבים. kabim. Okay. והכוז, vehakuz,
the pitcher, דומה לקיתון גדול, domeh lekiton gadol, it was like a
big pitcher, של זהב shel zahav and it was gold. ושתי מפתחות,
ushtei maftichos, and there were two
keys. אחד שהוא יורד באמת השחי, echad shehu yored be'amas hashachi, ואחד
שהוא פותח כיוון. ve'echad shehu pose'ach keivan. One that would go down
to the arm of the underarm is one way of reading it,
and I'll describe what that means in a minute, and the other
which would open up directly. What does this mean? It means that
they would use these as we'll see in a minute to get
into the remember we talked before that they would have little doors
in the middle of the big gate. Before they were ready to
open up all the gates, they still had to get access so
there would be doors, you know, built into the gate. So this
is true also about the gates of the עזרה. azara. Now one
of the important הלכות halachos is that you cannot שחט shacht the
תמיד, not only it has to be day, but it has to
be only after נפתחו דלתות ההיכל niftichu dolsos haheichal unless or היכל
heichal excuse me, היכל, heichal, only after the doors of not the
עזרה azara excuse me, היכל, heichal, only after the doors of the
היכל heichal have been opened because we learn it from a פסוק
pasuk of פתח אוהל מועד, pesach ohel mo'ed, the opening of the
אוהל מועד. ohel mo'ed. This represents the אוהל מועד ohel mo'ed that
they had in the time of the משכן, mishkan, the part that
was covered. So it has to have the doors, not only in
front of the door, but the door has to be פתוח, pasuach,
open. Okay, so that would be a big thing when finally like
that's when the עבודה avodah was really the מקדש mikdash was open
for business, you know, those doors opened and now they could start
the שחיטה, they could start the עבודה. avodah. Obviously the doors here
to be open would allow people to come in, but these doors
of the of the היכל heichal were open, allowed the שחיטה to
start. But they don't did not do that right away. There was
a little there was a little door built into the large gate
that they would get into to do the cleaning of the מזבח
Mizbe'ach, and the מנורה, menorah, right, before they're actually going to open
up the whole gate. So that's where having these keys for this
door built into the gate. Now why did they have two keys
and what does this mean בית השחי? beis hashachi? So there's different
interpretations, but some say basically that there was you had to have
like, you know, two locks, two keys at the same time in
the same lock, like coordinated and turn it at the same time
and one was from the inside and one was from the outside.
And of course there's a problem, how do you get in to
the inside lock? So that's what they say that there was a
little hole in the wall and you stuck your arm in the
hole and you sort of turned your arm
and
you
did... And the other person do the lock on the other side.
So כיבני kibeni means like directly.
What? That's awfully complicated.
Overcomplicated. Well others say it just means one was a lock below
and the other was a lock at the normal height, so בית
שחי beit shachi means from the word like לשוח lishoch to bend
down, so one would bend down to do the lock. So there's
different interpretations. Okay, but there were two locks that were going on
here.
One second, when was this open for people to actually...
Yeah, we haven't got to that yet. I think it's coming up.
Okay, not yet. Some people aren't even allowed in.
Right, right now it's just quiet, it's all the כהנים, nobody else
is in. And the...
and the sheep.
And the sheep. Okay, now, אחד בצפון ואחד בדרום. echad batzafon ve'echad
badarom. Now, now I'm sorry, שתי פשפשין היו לו לשער הגדול. shtei
pishpashin hayu lo lasha'ar hagadol. I'm sorry did I skip a line?
Okay, ואחד פותח כיבני בא לו לפשפש הצפוני. ve'echad pote'ach kibeni ba
lo lapishpash hatzefoni. He came to the northern פשפש, pishpash, I think
the northern small door inside of the gate. Now, שני פשפשין היו
לו לשער הגדול. shenei pishpashin hayu lo lasha'ar hagadol.
There were two of these little doors for the main gate, the
main gate of the היכל. heichal. אחת בצפון ואחת בדרום. achat batzafon
ve'achat badarom.
Yeah, I'm talking about this door right here for the היכל. heichal.
Okay? Two little doors. אחת בצפון ואחת בדרום, achat batzafon ve'achat badarom,
one in its northern half part and one in its southern. Okay,
שבדרום לא
נכנס בו אדם. shebadarom lo nichnas bo adam. And the one in
the south was never opened, nobody ever went through it. Why would
they... Let's take a look. עליו הוא מפורש על ידי יחזקאל. alav
hu meforash al yedei yechezkel. This is what... this is the one
that's referred to by יחזקאל yechezkel שנאמר, shene'emar, the פסוק pasuk says,
ויאמר ה' אלי, vayomer Hashem elai, God said to me, which is
interesting by the way because יחזקאל yechezkel has this prophecy about the
third בית המקדש beit hamikdash and
we're quoting him in reference to the second בית המקדש. beit hamikdash.
But anyway, God said to me, השער הזה סגור יהיה, hasha'ar hazeh
sagur yihyeh, this gate, here we're talking about a door in a
gate but that's how we're reading it, this gate will be closed,
לא יפתח, lo yipate'ach, it will never be opened, ואיש לא יבוא
בו, ve'ish lo yavo bo, no man will enter into this one,
כי ה' אלוהי ישראל בא בו. ki Hashem elokei yisrael ba bo.
בא בו. ba bo. בא בו. ba bo. Anyway, because Hashem the
God of Israel will enter into it,
no people will enter into it, ואיש לא יבוא בו, ve'ish lo
yavo bo, no man. Did I read... I reread it. No, I
read it. So והיה סגור, vehayah sagur,
and it will remain closed. So what does that mean? God is
going in that gate, not people? So, you know, the best is
one of the מפרשים mefarshim said what it's there to emphasize is
that God doesn't need doors to be open. So it doesn't, you
know, they start to take a little away from this very heavy
anthropomorphism, but it's really saying is for God to be present there
you, you human, need to open doors to get into a place.
This door's closed to show God can be wherever he wants without
there being having to open a door. Anyway, following this פסוק, pasuk,
and again it's interesting because the פסוק pasuk was said after the
חורבן churban of the בית. bayis. Anyway, they understood that there was
a door that was not open. נטל את
המפתח. natal es hamafte'ach. So you took the key, ופתח את הפשפש.
ufatach es hapishpash. You entered into... you opened up this little door
in the gate. נכנס לתא. nichnas lata. And you entered into the
like chamber, not exactly sure what the chamber is, it seems like
there's a little
space, maybe it was... maybe it means the hollow of the gate,
you know when you go through the door, you open the door
you have to get through the thickness of the gate, not exactly
sure what this chamber is. לתא, lata, ומתא להיכל. umita leheichal. And
from the chamber he finally entered into the היכל heichal proper, עד
שיגיע לשער הגדול. ad sheyagi'a lasha'ar hagadol. Until he came to the
great gate, which means again it's a little funny, great gate, you
were just passing through the gate, great gate, but anyway what it
basically means is you came out through this door and then you
turned so that you were facing the gate, the major gate, which
is you went through the door of the main gate but now
you're turning and you're facing the major gate because now you're going
to be the one to open the gate from the inside. It
was locked from the inside and it could only be opened from
the inside. Okay, הגיע לשער הגדול. higi'a lasha'ar hagadol. You came to
the main gate. העביר את הנגר. he'evir es hanagar. You removed the
bolt. Okay, so this was a thing which was... it had a
key, it had a huge bolt across it and it was bolted
on the inside. So you squeeze through this little door in the
gate, then you get to the actual mechanism of the gate itself
to the big bolt, ואת הפותחות. ve'es hapotechos.
And also the locks. It had a bolt and
locks. ופתחו. ufetacho. And you, so this is a nice little זכות.
zechus. Now you understand why this is the... you know, this is
the first... you know, nice thing to be upfront. You get to
be the one to open up the gate. Okay, so you opened
it up. לא היה שוחט שוחט. lo hayah shochet shochet. Now actually
there were two of you. There was the one doing the מזבח
Mizbe'ach. הפנימי and the one doing the
מנורה, Menorah but it's in the singular so it's not exactly clear
how they divided it. Could be it was a two-person job. לא
היה שוחט שוחט, lo hayah shochet shochet, or שוחט השוחט. shochet hashochet.
The slaughterer would not slaughter עד ששומע שער הגדול שנפתח. ad sheshome'a
sha'ar hagadol sheniftach. Until he hears the main gate which opened. until
he heard the main gate open up.
All right, because you have to have, it has to be light
and it has to be פתח אהל מועד, pesach ohel moed, so
the שער היכל shaar heichal has to be open. Now, מיריחו, MiYericho,
now we get into a nice little passage about hearing the gate
opening up and hearing other things in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
מיריחו היו שומעין קול שער הגדול שנפתח. MiYericho hayu shomein kol shaar
hagadol sheniftach.
From יריחו Yericho remember we mentioned... we mentioned Chevron, excuse me, not
Yericho. But anyway, all the way to יריחו Yericho they could hear
the sound of the opening of the gate. It was such a
huge gate. One imagines that if somebody was going to say, like
we said yesterday, גוזמא, guzma, that this might have been included. But
the גמרא Gemara never says גוזמא, guzma, treats this as literal. So
all the way to יריחו Yericho they could hear the opening of
the main gate of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, of the היכל.
Heichal. מיריחו היו שומעין קול מגריפה. MiYericho hayu shomein kol magreifa. From
יריחו Yericho they would hear the sound of the מגריפה magreifa which
would be one of the musical instruments that the לויים Leviyim would
play. According to some גרסאות, girsaot, מיריחו היו שומעין קול השיר, MiYericho
hayu shomein kol hashir, they would hear the sound of the actual
singing of the לויים. Leviyim. Some take that out. מיריחו היו שומעין
קול בן ארזא מקיש בצלצל. MiYericho hayu shomein kol Ben Arza makish
betziltzal.
They would hear the sound of בן ארזא Ben Arza who would
play the צלצל, tziltzal, one of these musical instruments. מיריחו היו שומעין
קול החליל, MiYericho hayu shomein kol hachalil, they would hear the sound
of the flute which was a instrument that they would play twelve
times in the year, the times that we say הלל, Hallel, specifically
we say הלל Hallel the days that they would play the flute.
מיריחו היו שומעין קול גביני כרוז, MiYericho hayu shomein kol Gevini Karoz,
they would hear the sound of the, also גביני כרוז Gevini Karoz
is I believe another musical instrument. מיריחו היו שומעין קול העץ שעשה
בן קטין מכונה לכיור, MiYericho hayu shomein kol ha'etz she'asa Ben Katin
mechona laki'or,
all the way to יריחו Yericho they could hear the sound of
the, you know, of the whole mechanical contraption that of wood that
they would use to lower
the כיור ki'or into the ground overnight so that it would not,
the water would not become פסול בלינה, pasul bilina, become invalid because
it stayed overnight. מיריחו היו שומעין קול שיר, MiYericho hayu shomein kol
shir, ah here's where they have the sound of the singing. They
would hear the sound of the singing all the way to יריחו.
Yericho. מיריחו היה שומע קול השופר, MiYericho haya shomeia kol hashofar,
they would hear the sound of the שופר shofar when they would
blow the שופר shofar on the קרבנות. korbanot. ויש אומרים אף קולו
של כהן גדול בשעה שהוא מזכיר את השם ביום הכיפורים. veyesh omrim
af kolo shel Kohen Gadol besha'ah shehu mazkir et HaShem beYom HaKippurim.
And some say they would even hear the sound of the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol when he said God's name on יום הכיפורים, Yom
HaKippurim, some say it doesn't literally mean the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
saying it, but it means everybody responding ברוך שם כבוד מלכותו לעולם
ועד. Baruch shem kevod malchuto l'olam va'ed. מיריחו היו מריחין ריח פיטום
הקטורת, MiYericho hayu merichin reiach pitum haktoret,
then they with they could even smell the burning incense, tying back
to the fact that we're about to burn, well actually we're not
about to burn the קטורת, ktoret, but we're cleaning up the מזבח,
so it's coming up anyway. Anyway, they could smell the burning of
the incense. אמר רבי אלעזר בן דגלאי עיזים היו לאבא בהרי מכוור
והיו מתעטשות מריח פיטום הקטורת. Amar Rabbi Elazar ben Diglai izim hayu
l'abba be'harei Michvar vehayu mitatshot mereiach pitum haktoret.
My father used to have goats in the cities of מכוור, Michvar,
wherever that was, some faraway village,
and they would pass gas by the smell
of the burning incense. So that's again an evidence about how faraway
it could be smelled. I was wondering, this is just total speculation,
but you know obviously there was a whole little rhythm, מיריחו היו
MiYericho hayu this, מיריחו היו MiYericho hayu that, מיריחו היו MiYericho hayu
that. I wonder if like maybe that was like ever a liturgy.
You know what I mean? Like you know some type of out
like you know you have those types of thing right, מראה כהן
גדול, Mareh Kohen Gadol, מראה כהן גדול, Mareh Kohen Gadol, you know
you have those מי שענה לאברהם, mi she'ana l'Avraham, מי שענה ליצחק.
mi she'ana l'Yitzchak.
Some of these early liturgies are very like repetitive like that. Of
course the ויש אומרים veyesh omrim doesn't fit in. But anyway, I
still wonder, it's very interesting the way to have that
repetition. Anyway, alright.
So not that far. 17 miles.
17 miles.
Oh, it wasn't a lot in between, think about it.
So here you could hear, and you could hear sound 17 miles
away?
In a valley you
could
hear, and
there are valleys that would echo. And smoke.
What? Maybe it's the smoke. And it's desert between ירושלים Yerushalayim and
יריחו. Yericho. It's a desert. Here they claim מתעטשות mitatshot is sneezing.
Oh,
sneezing, you're right. Because of the...
Right, yeah you're right, מתעטשות mitatshot means sneezing, not pass gas. Right,
yeah you're right, מתעטשות mitatshot means to sneeze.
You are correct, that makes more sense.
Right, right, you're correct, מתעטשות mitatshot means to sneeze. You are correct.
Okay, okay. Now, okay, so that was the, now so you got
in to do the דישון מזבח הפנימי והמנורה dishun mizbeiach hapnimi vehamenorah
and the first thing you did was you opened the gate so
now things are open for business, could be heard all the way
to יריחו. Yericho. Now, מי שזכה בתמיד משכו והולך לבית המטבחיים. Mi
shezacha batamid meshacho veholech leBeit HaMitbachayim.
So the one who is merited the תמיד, we're not yet... we
will talk in a minute about the actual דישון מזבח הפנימי dishun
mizbeiach hapnimi and the מנורה, but now we're back to the תמיד.
The one who merited the תמיד took the sheep because these things
are sort of happening in parallel. People are taking the sheep, then
these guys explain... no no no, they sent a group to לשכת
הטלאים, Lishkat Hatlaim, right it says before, go get a sheep from
לשכת הטלאים. Lishkat Hatlaim. Maybe he went with that group, maybe he
didn't, other people who were involved in the תמיד went that way.
As they were doing this, the person ran in and the people
that were doing the דישון מזבח הפנימי Dishun Mizbe'ach Hapnami and the
מנורה went in, the little door, opened the gate. Now we're switching
back to the sheep. So the person who's going to שחט shecht
the sheep, so he takes the sheep from the people that got
from the לשכת הטלאים. Lishkat Hatlayim. Where were we? מי שזכה בתמיד
משכו והלך בבית המטבחיים. Mi shezacha batamid moshcho vehalach beveit hamitbachayim.
And he went into the place of the slaughtering. ומי שזכו
באברים הולכים עמו, Umi shezachu baeivarim holchim imo, and I'll say in
a minute, and the people that are going to deal with the
limbs are going with him. So there's this big group. And again,
the assumption is that those people who are going to bring the
limbs up to the מזבח, they were the ones that got the
sheep from the לשכת הטלאים. Lishkat Hatlayim. Now where is this בית
המטבחיים, Beit Hamitbachayim, the slaughterhouse? So it says house, you think it's
a room, but no, it's referring to a location. בית המטבחיים היו
צפונו של מזבח. Beit Hamitbachayim hayu tzefono shel mizbe'ach. So it was
the north. So if you see in this picture, you see this
place where they have all of these circles. So those circles were
rings in which they either put the legs of the קרבן according
to the הרמב"ם, Rambam, according to most they put the heads of
the קרבן through those rings to keep them in place when they
were actually going to slaughter them. So this was the area that
they did the slaughtering. You will notice that it is צפון Tzafon
of the מזבח. It's the north of the מזבח, which is where
צפונה לפני השם, Tzafona lifnei Hashem, which is where the slaughtering of
the קדשי קדשים Kodshei kodashim was done, which was to the north
of the מזבח. So that area was called בית המטבחיים. Beit Hamitbachayim.
Okay, this was the slaughterhouse, the slaughter area. And over here you
had tables in which you would dismember them and in which you
would wash out the intestines. And so slaughtering here, chopping up, dismembering,
flaying, washing out the intestines, all of this, so this space was
called slaughterhouse. Okay. So בית המטבחיים היו צפונו של מזבח,
Beit Hamitbachayim hayu tzefono
shel mizbe'ach, it was to the north. ועליו ח' עמודים
ננסים, Ve'alav chet amudim nannasim, and there were eight short, ננסים nannasim
is a midget, eight, you know, miniature pillars. ורביעים של ארז על
גביהם, Ve'revi'im shel erez al gabeihem, and there were squares of cedar
wood on top of them. This is where they would do the
flaying. Some say that this was the same as we're going to
hear in a minute of the tables that they did where, you
know, or some say it was either the same or together with
the tables here where they washed out the innards, and some because
there were eight of those and some say no, they were sort
of directly in the middle of this area and they were separate
pillars. But anyway, so what did they do? Okay. ואונקלאות של ברזל
היו קבועים בהם. Ve'onkla'ot shel barzel hayu kevu'im bahem. And there were
iron hooks attached to them, to these square, no no, these wooden
squares that were on top of the pillars. Okay, this would basically
be the frame, that's a better word, a wooden frame that they
would use to stretch out the animal and to flay. וג' סדרים
לכל אחד ואחד. Ve'gimmel sedarim lechol echad ve'echad. And there were three
rows of these hooks for each one of these frames. ובהם תולים
ומפשיטים, Uvahem tolim u'mafshitim, and on them they would suspend and flay
the קרבנות. Why three? So some say actually there would be three
because of three sizes. You have sheep, you'd have goats, and you'd
have what do you call it, and you'd have cows. So certainly
cows are probably three times as big, so you know it wouldn't
just be that you'd need three rows of hooks, you'd also need
a
like a movable, like you know,
type of a adjustable size frame. Anyway, so they would hang them
on to them. Okay. ובהם תולים ומפשיטים. Uvahem tolim u'mafshitim. על שולחנות
של שיש שבין
העמודים. Al shulchanot shel shayish shebein ha'amudim. Now these would be on
these on
marble tables which were between the pillars. So again what does between
mean? Literally between the, yeah, between the, amidst, right. So it doesn't
mean here that they were sort of mixed in together... Anyway, the
way this is, is the pillars
were, the miniature pillars were here and they had these wooden tables
right near them, that's the way this picture, not wooden, marble, excuse
me, these marble tables right near them. מי שזכה בדישון מזבח הפנימי,
Mi shezacha
bidishun mizbe'ach hapnami,
now back to, we keep on switching our focus, back to the
cleaning out of the inner altar,
נכנס ונטל את הטני. Nichnas venatal et hateni. He went in and
he took the basket. So it's not exactly clear נכנס, nichnas, does
that mean he was already in because he went in to open
up the main gate? Does he now go in through the main
gate? Anyway, not exactly clear, but okay. It sounds before it says
that he went in to open up the gate, so it sounds
like he's already in. He took his gold basket. והניחו לפניו. Ve'hinicho
lefanav. He put the basket down on the floor. וחופן ונותן לתוכו.
Vechofen venoten letocho.
And he would, interestingly, the way he would clean the top of
the מזבח הפנימי would be with his hand. Yeah. וחופן, Vechofen, he
would scoop up
with his hands and put the ashes into the basket. Okay, that's
how he would do it. Why by hand? I don't know, maybe
you didn't need a כלי, kli, but you know you would wonder
like wouldn't it be
more proper... Valued 93 points? Sorry, didn't get that. Good question. Now
ובאחרונה u-bachrona after he did all the stuff he could scoop out
with his hands, כיבד את השאר לתוכו, kibed et hash'ar letocho, he
would sweep, like you know, the remainder so presumably he did have
some type of like a hand brush with him, although it didn't
say. It says he only had four vessels, doesn't say he brought
another type of a vessel, but somehow maybe he would just maybe
he did like this, you know, like when you sweep stuff off
the table, you know, it doesn't say how, but anyway, somehow he
would sweep the remainder in when he could no longer scoop it
up with his hand. והניחו v'hinicho and he would leave it there
ויצא, veyatza, so he didn't take out the basket, the basket was
left there, we're not done, okay, these things were sort of done
in stages. So he put it into the basket the ashes he
left. מי שזכה בדישון המנורה, mi shezacha bedishun hamenora, the one who
got the right for the Menorah, נכנס ומצא שתי נרות מערביות דולקות.
nichnas umatza shtei nerot ma'araviyot dolkot.
He found the two westernmost candles lit. Now, this whole discussion about
whether this is בדרך נס, bederech nes, why דווקא davka were those
done, what is the נר מערבי? ner ma'aravi? Basically, the point is
like this is that you would clean out the other, this first
עבודה avoda you would take out the ashes and the wicks and
if there's any leftover oil, clean it out, fill it up again,
put the new wicks in and so on. But we learn from
פסוקים psukim or whatever that it says יערוכנו הכהן, yaarchenu hacohen, יערוכנו
הכהן, yaarchenu hacohen, that there's two stages and each and each stage
has נרות, nerot, multiple wicks, multiple candles, so that you would do
the first stage you would do five and you would leave two
over and then do two at a second stage. Now, those two
were considered to be one of them was the נר מערבי. ner
ma'aravi. What was the נר מערבי ner ma'aravi is a whole debate.
Some say it means the Menorah was, well, first of all right,
if the Menorah was oriented east-west, right, and this is the west,
this is the קודש קודשים, kodesh kodashim, so the most logical thing
is the נר מערבי ner ma'aravi was the one here at the
most western facing the קודש קודשים, kodesh kodashim, that's the most west.
Or others say, I don't know, it means actually the one that
was at this end and this is what our Mishnah seems to
say, that there was an eastern and a western and the there
was a most eastern and the נר מערבי ner ma'aravi was the
one one in from the east, so it was west relative to
the outer one. The other explanation is that the Menorah was oriented
like this and the נר מערבי ner ma'aravi was the center one
facing to the west.
It was the other way.
What? I don't know. So let's just finish the Mishnah.
Wait, doesn't it say the two most western ones?
No, I know what it says. Let's just read it. מצא שתי
נרות מערביות דולקות, matza shtei nerot ma'araviyot dolkot, מדשן את השאר, medashen
et hash'ar,
so he would clean out the other five, ומניח את
אלו דולקות במקומן, umeniach et elu dolkot bimcoman, and he would leave
these two burning. Now, what if they weren't burning? So according to
some there was a נס nes that they were always burning, that
the נר מערבי ner ma'aravi would burn even a whole twenty four
hours even into the next night, but anyway, if this weren't burning,
if they were all burning, he would extinguish those that were burning
but leave these two burning. If none were burning, it's not spelled
out in the Mishnah, but presumably he would light these two. So
דווקא davka make sure that these, assuming that there was some wick
and oil left, I guess he'd have to add extra in order
to make sure, but all this was done in order to do
it in two stages. So you clean out the others, you leave
these burning or you make them burning if they're not burning. מצא
שכבו, matza shekavu, oh here it says, if you found that those
two had already extinguished, מדשנן ומדליקן מן הדולקים, medashnan umadlikan min hadolkim,
so then you clean them out, put in new wicks or whatever
or maybe whatever and you relight them from the ones that are
lit. ואחר כך v'achar kach מדשן את השאר, medashen et hash'ar, then
you clean out, meaning get them to be lit again, presumably the
assumption would be that by the next morning they would all still
be lit, so the normal case would be you extinguish five and
you leave two, but if the two you're supposed to leave had
gone out, you relight them so that then you can extinguish the
other five and these two will remain lit. And this is in
order to do it in two stages. ואבן הייתה לפני המנורה, v'even
hayta lifne hamenora, there was a stone in front of Menorah, ובה
ג' מעלות, ubbah gimel maalot, and there were three steps, שעליה כהן
עומד ומטיב את הנרות, she'aleha kohen omed umetiv et hanerot, that he
would stand up to light the to clean the נרות nerot and
to light them. I guess cleaning them requires more access than lighting
them, right, because you have to more manipulate. ומניח את הכוז על
מעלה שנייה umaniach et hakuze al ma'ala shniya
and then he put all the wicks and all the gunk he
put into this pitcher, that's why he had the pitcher, the same
reason the other one had the basket, ויצא veyatza and he left.
So now we've got everything in two stages. He put the stuff
in and he left, the other one put the ashes in and
left and there's two candles left of Menorah that have remained burning
or were relit and have to be finished, but we will continue
with this process tomorrow. Okay.